Guide to the Munson Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Munson family papers
1710-1888
MS 734
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
Correspondence, financial papers, and deeds of two branches of the Munson family of New Haven and nearby Connecticut towns. Most of the correspondence pertains to Edwin Beach Munson (1817-1879), his sons Albert L. Munson (b. 1842) and Edward Munson (b. 1854), and Edwin's brother Francis Munson (b. 1827), a book dealer in Chicago.Several letters ca. 1866 concern a patent for making paper napkins.The remaining papers, consisting of deeds and financial papers, relate to the family of Baszel Munson (1730-1803). An addition to the collection consists of a commonplace scraprook of Emily C. Munson of New Haven.
Munson family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from M. Earle, 1944 and 1946; transferred from Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, 1999
Scope and Contents
These papers consist of correspondence and legal and financial papers of two distantly related branches of the Munson family of New Haven and nearby towns in Connecticut.
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Munson family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Further details are available in The Munson Record by Myron A. Munson.
Most of the correspondence pertains to Edwin Beach Munson (1817-1879) and includes family letters from his brother Francis (1827-?), who was a book dealer in Chicago, and his sons Albert (1842-?) and Edward (1854-?), a few business letters, and some correspondence of other members of his family. Legal and financial papers from 1849 and 1879 relating to this branch of the family include the will of Charles Munson (1792-1879), various deeds to land in New Haven, receipts, and an unidentified photograph.
The rest of the papers stem from the family of Bazel Munson (1729-1803), and consist entirely of legal and financial papers dating from 1710 to 1844. Most are deeds for land in New Haven and vicinity, the earliest being a deed from David Yale (1693-1757) to Isaac Stiles, father-in-law of Bazel Munson. Papers other than deeds include promissory notes, lists of debts, a lease to Bazel Munson for a sawmill, and other similar items.
The Munson Family Papers were purchased by Yale University in 1944 and 1946.
Biographical / Historical
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Munson family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Families; Paper products; Middle West; New Haven (Conn.); Deeds; Patents (license); Munson, Albert L., 1842-; Munson, Baszel, 1730-1803; Munson, Edward, 1854-; Munson, Edwin Beach, 1817-1879; Munson, Francis, 1827-; Munson family
- Inventory, 1710-1879; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Letters of Francis Munson to Edwin B. Munson to Edwin B. Munson, 1872-1878 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Other correspondence, 1866-1879, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Legal and financial papers, 1710-1879, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-21)
    General note
    See also: MG Common folio, No.37
  - Receipts, 1872-1879 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Photograph (2 copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - OVERSIZE: Legal and financial Papers
    - 4 deeds, 1714, 1861 (Box 3)
    - MS list of deeds, 1794-1847, undated (Box 3)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-090
  - Munson, Emily C.
    - Commonplace scrapbook [Vol. 6, contains newspaper clippings and memorabilia pertaining to New Haven history, women's issues, literature and poetry], 1887 May-1888 November (Box 1)